A Guide to the Shoe research files, 1988
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
Colonial shoes research files 1988
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
MS 1993.11
.75 linear feet.
Documentation relating to colonial footwear compiled by Colonial Williamsburg's Historic Trades program for future reference and reproduction.
Colonial Williamsburg. Historic Trades.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Transfer from Historic Trades
Biographical/Historical Information
N/A
Scope and Content
These files are the result of a survey of surviving examples of eighteenth-century footwear conducted by Colonial Williamsburg employees in 1988. Each folder within the file documents a particular shoe examined and includes a sheet giving measurement, materials used, and information regarding the type of stitching and type of lining used, Each folder also includes a survey sheet, tracings of the various pieces used to construct the shoe, and a black and white photo of the shoe.
Arrangement
The folders are arranged by identification numbers assigned by the researchers.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Shoes
Contents List
- Colonial Shoes: 20th century research
  - Man's Turnshoe, England, business manufacture, ca. 1781; 0250
  - Woman's shoe, ca. 1781; 0440
  - Man's right shoe, ca. 1781; 0533
  - Sole, insole, one (attached) quarter heel lining belonging to one shoe. 2 quarters and latch appear to NOT be related to pattern and leather., ca. 1781; 0534
  - Shoe vamp, England, ca. 1781; 0537
  - Vamp only is in practically mint condition, ca. 1781; 0540
  - Man's shoe (vamp only), ca. 1781; 0680
  - Object is fine quality, intact, not pulled apart, ca. 1781; 0892
  - Man's heel and sole, ca. 1781; 0930
  - Man's vamp, ca. 1781; 0997
  - Sailor's shoe, England, ca. 1781; 1011
  - Man's shoe, ca. 1781; 1013
  - Man's shoe, ca. 1781; 1032
  - Sole only, ca. 1781; 1049
  - Two pieces of heel, England, ca. 1781; 1063
  - Rear half of outer sole and heel, England, ca. 1781; 1065
  - Man's turnsole, England, ca. 1781; 1109
  - Sailor shoe, England, ca. 1781; 1123
  - This shoe has overlapping stitching intact on right quarter, ca. 1781; 1155
  - Turnshoe sole and heel, England, ca. 1781; 1211
  - Man's shoe, ca. 1781, 1236
  - Man's turnshoe, England, business manufacture, ca. 1781; 1266
  - Man's shoe (1/2 sole only), ca. 1781; 1272
  - Man's shoe (sole only), ca. 1781; 1300
  - Sailor's shoe (insole only), England business manufacture, ca. 1781; 1347
  - Man's shoe, ca. 1781; 1361
  - Pieces of man's shoe (latches), England, ca. 1781; 1399
  - Man's work shoe (turnshoe with insole), England, ca. 1781; 1400
  - Man's shoe parts, ca. 1781; 1444
  - Sailor's shoe, England, ca. 1781; 1443
  - Man's shoe parts, ca. 1781; 1445
  - Sailor's shoe, England, ca. 1781; 1404
  - Turnshoe/insole, buckled, clump sole repair, England, ca. 1781; 1450
  - Man's shoe (vamp only), ca. 1781; 1542
  - Man's shoe parts, ca. 1781; 1563
  - Man's shoe, business manufacture, ca. 1781; 1608
  - Man's shoe parts, England, ca. 1781; 1612
  - Sailor shoe, England, ca. 1781; 1613
  - Sailor shoe insole, turnsole, England, ca. 1781; 1673
  - Sailor shoe, England, ca. 1783; 1679
  - Sailor's shoe, England, ca. 1781; 1764
  - Sailor shoe (piece of heel), England, ca. 1781; 1790
  - Man's shoe part (sock liner only), ca. 1781; 1972
  - Sailor shoe (heel only), England, ca. 1781; 1800
  - Sailor shoe (2 quarters only), England, ca. 1781; 1821
  - Man's dress shoe, England, business manufacture, ca. 1781; 1822
  - Man's shoe, ca. 1781; 1824
  - Man's shoe, ca. 1781; 1881
  - Man's shoe, England, business manufactured, ca. 1781; 1882
  - Sailor's turnshoe, heavily patched, England, business manufactured, ca. 1781; 1848
  - Man's shoe (not disassembled), England, ca. 1781; 1886
  - Man's shoe vamp (fragment only), ca. 1781; 1995
  - Sailor's shoe, England, ca. 1781; 3941
  - Sailor's shoe (welt), England, ca. 1781; 3972
  - Sailor's shoe (welt), England, maker's name is C.H. or H.C., ca. 1781; 5085
  - Man's shoe, England, business manufacture, ca. 1781; 17495